<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first part of Babel's-builders unmasking themselves as appears by the following judgment from Barbadoes (promoted by George Fox his party, and subscribed by eighty two of them) : with a letter of G.F.'s, G.W's, &amp;c. in answer thereunto, and observations thereupon : also a false prophesie of that lying prophet, Sol. Eccles : whereas the following discourse was formerly printed and privately disposed ... amongst those called Quakers, but finding some of G.F.'s party have since publickly exposed it with slanderous and false charges on the author, this second impression with some small addition, is now made publick ... / Thomas Crisp.</title>
            <title>Babel's-builders unmask't. Part 1</title>
            <author>Crisp, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35009</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6951</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10390</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12533962</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12533962</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62825</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35009)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62825)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 311:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first part of Babel's-builders unmasking themselves as appears by the following judgment from Barbadoes (promoted by George Fox his party, and subscribed by eighty two of them) : with a letter of G.F.'s, G.W's, &amp;c. in answer thereunto, and observations thereupon : also a false prophesie of that lying prophet, Sol. Eccles : whereas the following discourse was formerly printed and privately disposed ... amongst those called Quakers, but finding some of G.F.'s party have since publickly exposed it with slanderous and false charges on the author, this second impression with some small addition, is now made publick ... / Thomas Crisp.</title>
                  <title>Babel's-builders unmask't. Part 1</title>
                  <author>Crisp, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
                  <author>Eccles, Solomon, 1618-1683.</author>
                  <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Enock Prosser ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>First of six parts. Originally issued as: Babel's builders unmasking themselves. 1681.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fox, George, 1624-1691 --  Theology.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Barbados.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62825:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FIRST PART OF Babel's-Builders <hi>Vnmasking Themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As appears by the following Judgment from <hi>Barbadoes</hi> (promoted by <hi>George Fox</hi> his Party, and ſubſcribed by Eighty two of them.) With a LETTER of <hi>G. F</hi>'s. <hi>G. W</hi>'s. &amp;c. in Anſwer thereunto; and <hi>Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> thereupon. Alſo, A <hi>Falſe Propheſie</hi> of that Lying Prophet <hi>Sol. Eccles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas the following <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> was formerly Printed and privately Diſpoſed, to thoſe Concerned, or privy to the Controverſie depending, amongſt thoſe called <hi>Quakers,</hi> but finding ſome of <hi>G. F</hi>'s. Party have ſince Publickly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it with <hi>Slanderous</hi> and <hi>falſe Charges</hi> on the Author, This ſecond Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, with ſome ſmall Addition, is now made Publick, in Deteſtation of the Principle contained in the <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>G. F. &amp;c.</hi> Being of Evill tendency, and contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt, his Apoſtles, and all ſincere-hearted Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>Alſo, in Expectation it may be of Service to thoſe who do not deſire to GIVE UP THEIR WHOLE CONCERNS SPIRETUAL AND TEMPORAL, IF RE-QUIRED, TO THE SPIRIT OF GOD (as they term it) IN THEIR MEN AND WOMENS MEETINGS. But for thoſe that have ſo done, (as is too Obvious there be many ſuch) that the Lord would give them to ſee the Errour of their Ways, and Repentance before it be too late, is the Deſire of, <hi>Thomas Criſp.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hosts, Hearken not unto the Words of the Prophets, that Propheſie unto you — They ſpeak a Viſion of their own Hearts, and not out of the Mouth of the Lord,</p> 
               <bibl>Jer. 23.16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Thy Prophets have ſeen Vain and Fooliſh Things for thee, and they have not diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered Thine Iniquity — but ſeen for thee Falſe Propheſies,</p> 
               <bibl>Lam. 2.14.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Enock Proſſer,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> in <hi>Swithins-Alley,</hi> at the Eaſt end of the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="introduction">
               <pb facs="tcp:62825:2"/>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62825:2"/>
               <head>The INTRODUCTION.</head>
               <p>THE Intent of the Publication of this enſuing Paper and Letter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is not to riflect on, or reproach the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> or in contempt of their Principle: For God hath a People among them, many of whom have long been reviled, and falſly accuſed and ſlandered, becauſe they have Conſcientiouſly refuſed to Conform to Preſcriptions without Conviction, and are therefore termed <hi>Seperates, Stubborn, Cains, Judas's, Apoſtates;</hi> and what not, that may make them odious to honeſt People? But this is to manifeſt the Apoſtacy and Innovations of a few of them that are of the <hi>Foxonian</hi> Sect [<hi>the term,</hi> Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onion, <hi>is only for Diſtinction</hi>] which love Preheminence, and term themſelves the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Elders,</hi> and the Church, and preſume to give Laws and Orders to others to Conform to, or elſe be accounted <hi>Infidels, Rebels,</hi> &amp;c. when it is evident, the Cauſe of their Rage againſt them (they call <hi>Separates,</hi> &amp;c.) is, becauſe they will not rebel againſt the Light in their own Hearts: So it is thoſe that pretend themſelves the Church, Elders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that would cauſe the People to rebel, therefore it may be ſaid, they are like <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the Son of <hi>Nebat,</hi> who made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to Sin. Alſo <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. have manifeſted themſelves to be <hi>Lo here's</hi> (which Christ commanded ſhould not be gone after) as appears by their Letter herein, produced and pretended as a Diſowning that Paper or Judgment, but doth chiefly endeavour to ſtifle it from going abroad, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it manifeſts their Confuſion.</p>
               <p>And that <hi>G. F's,</hi> &amp;c. Univerſal Spirit they ſo often mention, is not that which <hi>Peter</hi> had, <hi>Acts 10, 24</hi> which accepts all that fear God, and work Righteouſneſs, but they hedge up the way to Acceptance with God, and leave no Entrance, but by their Forms of Men and Womens-Meetings; contrary to Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>I am the Way;</hi> &amp;c. Alſo they aſcribe that to their Orders and Meetings, which the Scripture aſcribes to Chriſt. And <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. are ſo fond of Proſelites to their Orders and Meetings, that notwithſtanding this Paper and Judgment is ſo repugnant to their pretended Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation-Principle, yet they give not a word of ſharp Reproof to it in all their Letter, as the Apoſtle to the <hi>Galatians, Who hath bewitched you?</hi> But they, inſtead thereof, give high Commendations: Therefore with Sorrow it may be ſaid, as formerly of Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſo now of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> from above, <hi>Her Adverſaries are the Chief, her Enemies prevail; and Blindneſs is in part happened to Iſrael.</hi> This hath the Lord ſuffered to come to paſs, that no Fleſh ſhould glory in his Sight. Therefore he humbled and fear before Him, for their preſuming that they are Gods People, and that they have his Wiſdom and Power with them, therefore they conclude, what they do act as the Body or Church, is of God, and must stand as his Will and Counſel, and for want of his Power (which alone makes his Peeple willing) they fly to their pretended Church Power and Authority, and <hi>Saul</hi>-like, deſire to have Honour before the People; but what Power theirs is, on which they ground their Authority to proceed againſt the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters from their preſcribed Forms of Meetings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hear <hi>Iſ. Penington's</hi> Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>That Power therefore in the Church which ſpares the Hippocrites (who can eaſily comply with an Outward Conformity in Worſhip, without feeling an Inward Life and Virtue) but lights heavy on that which is tender and ſhy in Matters of Worſhip, that is not the true Church-Power, at beſt, but a Counterfeit of the True.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62825:3"/>
               <head>At a Quarterly-Meeting at <hi>Ralph Fretwell's</hi> Houſe in <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> the 23d. day of the tenth Month, <hi>1680.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Sum of the Teſtimony this day born, amounts to this: That there is this day a Choice to be made, <hi>Viz.</hi> Whether Friends will cleave and abide unto the Univerſal Spirit of the Living God, and each give up their whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns; with which Spirit the Faithful have Unity? Or, Whether they will give up unto the Judgment in their own particular, or Particulars only, with which the Judgment General of the Meeting have not Unity?</p>
               <p>After very many Teſtimonies given, to the further opening of the Queſtion, the Judgment underneath was written, being voluntarily Subſcribed unto by each particular of this Meeting, or by their Orders, their Names were hereunto put.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="judgment">
                           <head>Here follows that Deteſtable Judgment aforementioned.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>I deſire to give up my whole Concern <hi>[then all Faith and Conſcience]</hi> if requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, both</hi> Spiritual <hi>&amp;</hi> Temporal, <hi>unto the Iudgment of the Spirit of God in the Men &amp; Womens Meetings: as believing it to be more according to the Vniverſal Wisdom of God, than any particular meaſure in my ſelf, or any particulars with which the Men &amp; Womens-Meetings have not Vnity.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>This wicked Judgment was Subſcribed by Men, 39. Women 43. Total 82.</p>
               <p>The Party that ſent the above-ſaid, writes thus, <hi>Viz.</hi> This Paper hath been promoted in ſundry other Meetings ſince, and Subſcribed: ſome few have refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: in abhorrence whereof, other Perſwaſions have Poſted it.</p>
               <p>Here follows the Letter of <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. to the Quarterly-Meeting at <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> touching the ſaid Paper; whereby it may be ſeen how, and wherein they own or diſown it.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <p>NOw dear Friends, if this <hi>Order</hi> or <hi>Judgment</hi> ſhould come into the hands of any <hi>Apoſtates</hi> or <hi>Oppoſers,</hi> they would make ill Work with it, and ſay, that we ſet up an Arbitrary Power over Mens Conſciences and Properties, and an Implicit Faith and Submiſſion, without Inward Conviction; <hi>[What more true]</hi> And that we divided the Meaſure of God in a particular, from the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Spirit of God in other Particulars in <hi>Mens</hi> and <hi>Womens-Meetings.</hi> And as for Subſcribing unto ſuch an <hi>Order</hi> or <hi>Judgment,</hi> they would ſay, it was like the <hi>Scotch-Covenant;</hi> and as tho the Meaſure of the Faith and Spirit of God in themſelves, was not agreeable to the Univerſal Spirit &amp; Faith in the <hi>Mens</hi> and <hi>Womens-Meetings;</hi> and that if they ſhould go from the Meaſure of Faith and Spirit of God in their own Particulars, and to give up both their <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal</hi> Concerns to the Univerſal Spirit in <hi>Mens</hi> and <hi>Womens-Meetings.</hi> This would be the way to bring them all from the Meaſure of the Spirit in their own Particulars. For how can the Men and Women in the Univerſal Spirit receive that which is not given up from the Univerſal Spirit: therefore all muſt be left to the Univerſal Spirit in their own Meaſures thereof; and as for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62825:3"/>
the <hi>Stubborn</hi> and <hi>Wilful,</hi> that are againſt <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Womens-Meetings,</hi> the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Spirit cannot receive that. And all are to give up to the Univerſal Spirit in their own Particulars, in which Spirit they have Unity and Fellowſhip without outward Subſcription, and to be led by the ſame Spirit, to ſee their Names written in Heaven in this Goſpel-day of Light and Life; and this is, and was the Saints Teſtimony in the New-Covenant of Light and Life, and their Heavenly Subſcription, which is above all outward Subſcriptions, both among the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> for the one ties them below, and the other ties them above. And for any to ſay, <hi>They deſire to give up their whole Concerns, both Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal unto the Judgment of the Spirit of God in Mens and Womens-Meetings, as believing it to be more according to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Wiſdom of God, than any particular Meaſure in my ſelf, or any Particulars.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Now this would make the Belief which is in the Light, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in their own Particulars, not one with the Univerſal Spirit in the ſaid Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. And as for thoſe that the <hi>Mens</hi> and <hi>Womens-Meetings</hi> in the Univerſal Spirit of God have not Unity with, they are erred from their own Meaſures of the Spirit of God; but the Univerſal Spirit of God has Unity with the the leaſt Meaſure now, as it was in the Apoſtles days, who kept every one to their own Meaſures, which was both the great Rule and Line of the new Creature in the Believers and Saints then, and ſo with that the Univerſal Spirit in the Apoſtles and Elders then had, and now have Unity. And therefore, dear Friends, we know your Care and Tenderneſs of Truth, and that you aim at the <hi>beſt Things, (Contrary to</hi> S. Criſp, <hi>who ſaid, the Paper was not only ill worded, but he believed 'twas ill meant)</hi> 'and have had much to do with ſome looſe Spirits there: and therfore our Deſires are, that you would ſtop this Paper from going any further, leſt ſome ſhould get Copies of it, and ſpread amongſt bad Spirits; and keep in the general tender Spirit of God, that in Love you may anſwer the Meaſure of the Spirit of God in them that are Convinced by it, and in them that err from it. <hi>And the Man of God muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle towards all.</hi> And ſo concluding with the Apoſtles tender Advice, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Now I beſeech you Brethren, by the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that you all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no Diviſions among you, but that you be perfectly joyned together in the ſame Mind, and in the ſame Judgment.</hi> And <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.2, 3. <hi>Fulfil you my Joy, that you be like minded, having the ſame Love, being of one Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, of one Mind, let nothing be done through Strife or vain Glory, but in lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of Mind let each eſteem other better than themſelves.</hi> And 1 Pet. 5.8. <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, be all of one Mind, having Compaſſion one of another, love as Brethren: Be pittiful, be courteous.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Now as for your Subſcription to an outward tie, be above ſuch things; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as you are manifeſtly declared to be the Epiſtle of Chriſt, written not with Ink, but with the Spirit of the Living God; which Spirit hath given you Life, and will bring you to the City of the Living God, the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to the General Aſſembly and Church of the Firſt-born, which are written in Heaven, <hi>&amp;c. Your dear Friends and Brethren in our Lord Jeſus Christ, in whom you have</hi> Peace, Life, <hi>and</hi> Salvation.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>GEORGE FOX, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62825:4"/>As for the aforeſaid Paper from <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> wherein is expreſt the Judgment of the Quarterly-Meeting, I take it to be neither according to Scripture, nor the Principles of Truth.</p>
               <p>And firſt, for Scripture; By it you make void the New-Covenant, or Law written in the Heart. Of which it is ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.11. <hi>They ſhall not need to teach every Man his Brother, ſaying, Know the Lord; but all ſhall know me from the least to the greatest.</hi> And John 2. <hi>The Anointing which you have received of Him, abideth in you, you need not any Man to teach you, but as that teacheth,</hi> &amp;c. But your Judgment contradicts theſe, <hi>Viz. (Give up your whole Concern, Spiritual and Temporal, if required, unto the Spirit of God,</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>in Men and Womens-Meetings, believing it to be more according to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Wiſdom of God, than any particular in your ſelves,</hi> &amp;c. But the Scripture ſaith, <hi>None know the Things of God, but the Spirit of God.</hi> And how ſhall any one know what the Meeting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires is according to the Spirit of God, if not by a meaſure of it in themſelves? It is alſo ſaid, <hi>If our Heart Condemn us, God is greater: but if that Coodemn us not, then have we Confidence towards God.</hi> For if it pleaſe God to reveal any thing to any Particular, and the general deny, or diſown it, then that particular muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Revelation, and give up to the general. According to this Doctrine, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee how the Church ſhould ever be reſtored out of the Apoſtacy, unleſs God firſt reveal Himſelf to the general; which ſeems to be contrary to His way of Manifeſtation to this very day: For what muſt <hi>John</hi> have done with his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Meſſage to the <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches, <hi>Sardis</hi> and <hi>Laodicia, who had a Name to Live, and were Dead? And ſaid, they were rich, and encreaſed in Goods, and wanted nothing.</hi> They thought well of themſelves, (as you do) &amp; had but few Names left (not the generality) yet were miſtaken, and Apoſtatized, and reproved by a Particular. Now, according to your Judgment, <hi>John</hi> and the <hi>few Names</hi> ought to have given up to the general, and not to his particular Revelation. Alſo all the Reformations ſince the <hi>Apostacy,</hi> have been begun by Particulars, and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and perſecuted by the general; therefore it is not as you ſay, <hi>moſt agreeing to the Wiſdom of God, to cleave to the Judgment of the general,</hi> but to the particular Manifeſtation; altho the Judgment general hath not Unity therewith. For if a Particular may reprove the general, ſurely he ought to cleave to his particular Meaſure for his own Belief and Practice, altho the general have not Unity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: <hi>for what is not of Faith, is Sin,</hi> much more what is contrary thereto. For if any Meeting requires one to do or believe contrary to their own Meaſure: who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever obeys them, therein becomes a Servant to thoſe Perſons &amp; Meetings: for <hi>his Servants ye are whom you obey.</hi> Hereby you call ſuch Men or Meetings your <hi>Maſter</hi> or <hi>Father,</hi> contrary to Chriſts Command. Oh Friends, ſtrain not at <hi>Gnats,</hi> and ſwallow ſuch <hi>Camels!</hi> which the 82 ſeemed to have done.</p>
               <p>That it is againſt the Principles of Truth, is plain enough, and needs no proof: for by that we are taught to be guided by the Manifeſtation of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in our own Hearts, to ſpeak and act as thereby inſtructed, and that the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Truth through a part of Chriſt's Members, cannot become a Bond on others further than their Underſtandings are illuminated thereby. Theſe two
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62825:4"/>
Poſitions the Judgment aforeſaid ſeems to contradict. Alſo read <hi>E. B.</hi> and <hi>Iſ. P</hi>'s Works, or any antient Friends, they all direct to the Light in our own Hearts or Conſciences, as the only and ſufficient Guide and Leader: But your Judgment not only contradicts Scripture, and Friends Teſtimonies, but you have given ſuch an unlimited Power to Meetings, and not contented to give that to Men which never before was given ſince <hi>Proteſtantiſm,</hi> but to Women alſo, in which the Scripture is ſilent; or what it ſays is rather againſt their having any Power or Rule, but to be ſubject. Nay, this unlimited Power was one of the heavy weights in the Pope's Yoke, that made it ſo uneaſy to <hi>England</hi> in times of <hi>Popery;</hi> neither can I find that ever in <hi>England,</hi> the Pope, or any Church, gained this point by all their Stratagems, Wars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as you have granted, (<hi>Viz.</hi> the giving up all Spirituals and Temporals) The Chriſtian-State is ſaid to be a <hi>glorious Liberty,</hi> but your Judgment makes them Slaves and Vaſſals, and will cauſe any Underſtanding Men to avoid ſubmitting to ſuch a Church that hath ſo unlimited a Power; 'tis much ſafer ſubmitting to a Church which makes the Scripture their Rule; for thereby one may know what they may or can require of one, but yours, (after one hath given up all Spirituals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) may ſtill require more without meaſure, if you pretend or ſtamp ſuch Requirings with the Name of the Univerſal Spirit of God, as Experience teacheth, hath been too frequent. What is become of all our Proteſting Fore-fathers, according to your Judgment? For you ſeem to have acquitted <hi>Rome</hi> of all their <hi>Blood,</hi> for they had not only the Judgment of the generality of the Church, but of the Magiſtracy and Law of the Nation againſt them, which was of greater Authority than your <hi>Womens Meetings,</hi> for which there is no Precept, Precedent nor Law, but againſt, <hi>viz.</hi> their Form and Power. I am aſhamed, that after all this Light and Knowledge pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, any ſhould make ſuch a long ſtride towards <hi>Rome,</hi> which now is very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable; for if but one more ſuch, I know not but you may both too ſoon meet, and embrace each other. If any ſay we miſtake you, you do not give up to the Meeting, but to the Spirit of God, <hi>&amp;c. W. Pen</hi>'s <hi>Addreſs,</hi> &amp;c. and other Teſtimonies, I think, anſwer that, <hi>Viz. A Man may falſly believe as the True Church believes: and if I believe only, becauſe She believes, and not becauſe I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced in my own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding and Conſcience, my Faith is falſe, tho Hens be true.</hi> p. 146. Alſo <hi>E. Burrough</hi> ſaith, <hi>Every one is to mind the Teachings of the Spirit of Chriſt in himſelf, for to that he is to ſtand or fall,</hi> p. 152. Alſo if a bare ſaying it is the Spirit without evidence will ſerve, then the Pope may ſay ſo to. Now that which further aggravates, and makes this Judgmen the worſe, is, that it ſhould come from ſuch Perſons as <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. writes the 82 Subſcribers to be, <hi>Viz. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly declared the Epistle of Christ, written with the Spirit of the Living God, which Spirit hath given you Life, and will bring you to the City of the Living GOD,</hi> &amp;c. —<hi>Aim at the beſt Things,</hi> Viz. <hi>Give up all,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>HIGH GROWN CRISTIANS, OR <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. HIGHLY MISTAKEN!</p>
               <p>Thus what you have done ſeems to be to the diſhonour of Truth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what you once profeſſed: for the ſufficiency of Light in your own
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62825:5"/>
hearts was that Goſpel you received, and they Preached at firſt, for all to cleave to, and abide by, and give up to. But now to give up to the Requirings of others altho con rary to that; what more like another Goſpel? Therefore I beſeech you, mind the Exhortation, <hi>If We, or an Angel from Heaven bring any other Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel than that you have received, let Him be accurſed.</hi> And avoid all ſuch Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as theſe are, and the Propounders thereof, for they are but fooliſh Queſtions, yea, worſe, and will gender to S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rife and BONDAGE; therefore let no Men (nor WOMEN eſpecially) rule over you, nei her receive their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions for Doctrines, further than manifeſted by the Truth in your own hearts, and in the Scriptu es Are you ſo fooliſh as to believe that the R quirings of Men and Women-Mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ings, without Scripture-Evidence, or manifeſtation by the Light in your own Hearts, can give you acceptance with God? wh n as Chriſt ſaid to them that ſaid they had Propheſied, and caſt out Devi s, and done many mighty Works in his Name, <hi>Depart, I know you not,</hi> &amp;c. And think you ſuch unwarrantable Requirings, and Implicit giving up, can ſtand you in ſtead? Nay, this Perſwaſion cometh not of God, but it is fulfilled, as was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied in Scripture, <hi>Some ſhall ariſe from among your ſelves, ſpeaking perve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe things.</hi> Remember from whence ye are fallen, and return to the meaſure of Truth in your own ſelves, and ariſe and depart from ſuch Judgmen s, for fear it be fulfilled on you, as was ſaid againſt ſome of old, <hi>When they knew God, they glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifi'd Him not as God; they became vain in their Imaginations, and their fooliſh hearts were darkened.</hi> Therefore I pray be not ſo ſoon moved and toſſed up and down by theſe windy Arbitrary and Implicit Judgm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nts of men, who have mens Perſons and Orders in Admiration, becauſe of Advantage; for ſuch ſerve not Chriſt, but themſelves: but mind you the Truth in your own hearts, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Let every one be fully perſwaded in his own Mind.</hi> You muſt anſwer for your ſelves to God, when it ſhall be ſaid, <hi>Who required theſe things at your hands?</hi> Will any <hi>Men</hi> or <hi>Women,</hi> or <hi>outward written Orders,</hi> have greater Force than <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets?</hi> Nay, but as many as are led by the Spirit of God, are the Sons of God; this Spirit Chriſt ſaid he would ſend, ſhould be in them.</p>
               <p>Foraſmuch as the foregoing Letter of <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. to <hi>Barbadoes</hi> was produced, as a proof of their denial of the ſaid Paper, I obſerve therein, That they are more afraid of its Publication, than aſhamed of the Matter, and do more object the ſubſcribing the Paper, than owning that Principle; (Viz, <hi>giving up all to them</hi>) as appears by their Words, <hi>If it ſhould come into the Hands of Oppoſers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they would ſay we ſet up Arbitrary Power, Implicit Faith,</hi> &amp;c. (but they ſay not ſo) which are the plain tendency thereof.</p>
               <p>But it is needful to know what they mean by the Univerſal Spirit, being that is ſo often mentioned. I take it to be the Opinion or Judgment of the Ruling Party (or <hi>Foxonions</hi>) among the <hi>Quakers;</hi> becauſe they exclude thoſe who op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their Orders, as being Apoſtates, and gone out from the Univerſal Spirit. Alſo I take this Spirit of theirs not to be the Univerſal Spirit of God, but a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62825:5"/>
private ſelfiſh Spirit of their own: becauſe they ſay, <hi>As for the Stubborn and Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that are againſt Men and Womens-Meetings, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spirit cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that.</hi> Now thoſe they term <hi>Stubborn,</hi> &amp;c. are not againſt Mens and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens-Meetings, but differ about the Form and Power thereof; they are only againſt Women having Meetings apart from the Men, when they have no buſineſs requires it: not againſt them in Cities, great Towns and Places, where they live near together, and Occaſions require, but where they live remote from each other, and have no buſineſs. Alſo the Form of Marriages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is great part of the difference, and the Caſe of thoſe Perſons, <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. term <hi>Apoſtates, Bad Spirits,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. ſays, <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spirit cannot receive that.</hi> I ſhall ſhew by Teſtimonies of Scripture and Friends, that notwithſtanding Differences, yet <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ought to receive each other, and walk in Love as Brethren.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>E. Burrough</hi> ſays, <hi>Notwithſtanding their difference in Judgment, whether in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Subſtantial or Ceremonial, yet they were ſtill to be in Love and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> pag. 809. <hi>And every one to mind the Teachings of the Spirit in himſelf.</hi> Hereby you may ſee that <hi>E. B.</hi> could receive in Love, and walk in Unity with ſuch as differed in Caſes Subſtantial: which is as high a difference as any about Womens Meetings can be.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>W. Pen</hi> ſaith (<hi>Addreſs to Proteſtants,</hi> p. 70.) <hi>I cannot ſee how ſuch Men can excuſe themſelves from great preſumption,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>who deny thoſe Perſons to be Members of Christ's Church, that in Conſcience refuſe to ſubſcribe any other Draught than their Lord hath given them.</hi> Then how can <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. excuſe themſelves, who ſay, <hi>Thoſe that be againſt Womens-Meetings, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spirit cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive?</hi> Unleſs <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. prove that ſuch Diſſenters have had their Form of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens-Meetings from the Lord. And <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. muſt admit them <hi>Members</hi> of Chriſts Church, or prove they refuſe that which the Lord hath given them; or elſe <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. are inexcuſable, and condemnable by their own Teſtimonies. Alſo 2 Pet. 1.5. <hi>Give all diligence thereunto: add to Faith, Vertue, Knowledge, Temperance, Patience, Godlineſs, Brotherly-Kindneſs, Love: for if theſe things be in you, and abound, ye ſhall not be unfruitful, nor barren,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>Wherefore give all diligence to make your Calling and Election ſure: for if ye do theſe things, ye ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fail; for an Entrance ſhall be miniſtred unto you into the Everlaſting Kingdom.</hi> Now I appeal to any ſober Chriſtian, Whether all theſe Qualifications may not be in one, and yet conſcientiouſly diſſent from a Form of <hi>Marriage,</hi> or <hi>Womens-Meetings,</hi> as order'd by <hi>G. F.</hi> If it can be, as I am ſure it may, that one may be ſo qualified and aſſiſted by Gods Spirit, as to attain theſe Vertues expreſſed by the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> and not comply with <hi>G. F</hi>'s Womens-Meetings; then a ſure entrance is made into the Everlaſting Kingdom, and they are received by the Univerſal Spirit of God: therefore <hi>G. F</hi>'s &amp;c. Univerſal Spirit, ſo often menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, is not that of God, nor of <hi>E. B.</hi> or <hi>Iſ. P.</hi> nor the Spirit of Chriſt nor his Apoſtles, for they ſaid, <hi>Judge not;</hi> and that the Tree was known by its Fruit. But <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. will judge and condemn for evil, and gone from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, altho no evil Fruit appears, only <hi>Nonconformity to them.</hi> Alſo where evil
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62825:6"/>
Fruit does appear, as in this their Judgment, yet he can ſay to them, becauſe they own his Form, and Womens Meetings, <hi>We know your Care, and that you aim at the beſt things.</hi> So that to give up to his Orders, tho contrary to their own meaſures, ſeems by him, termed the <hi>beſt Things,</hi> and they are <hi>manifeſtly declared the Epiſtle of Christ, wrote with the Spirit of the Living God,</hi> &amp;c. Whereby he ſeems to place more Vertue and Power in conforming to his Orders of Womens Meetings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than in all Faith and Fruits of the Spirit, expreſſed in the Scripture. And where-ever <hi>G. F.</hi> mentions the Univerſal Spirit, I take him he meanes the Spirit that ſet up, and adores thoſe <hi>Meetings,</hi> and perſecutes all ſuch who cannot for Conſcience ſake conform thereto. Now Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Whatever you would ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould do unto you, that do unto them. Love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> &amp;c. This is the true Univerſal Spirit, to deſire no more Liberty nor Charity from another than one would be content to allow them; and Impoſe no more on another, than one would have them Impoſe on ones ſelf. <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. once cryed for <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience;</hi> none muſt perform any <hi>Worſhip,</hi> but as taught and led thereinto by the Light in their own Hearts: but having gathered a People to themſelves, now (ſay they) <hi>Submit to your Elders:</hi> and if not Conform to his Orders (for Conſcience ſake) then <hi>Wilful, Stubborn, out of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spirit and Truth, Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Rebels, accurſed from all Eternity,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And it appears that the Subſcribers and <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. do differ: for he ſays, <hi>This would make the Belief which is in the Light, and the meaſure of the Spirit in their own particulars, not one with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal (i. e.</hi> G. F's) <hi>Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. Indeed ſo it doth; for there be many that believe in the Light, and meaſure of the Spirit, and its Sufficiency, that are not one with <hi>G. F</hi>'s, &amp;c. Impoſing Spirit, which he calls <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> but againſt it; altho the true Univerſal Spirit of Chriſt, and in all His, hath now, as formerly, Unity with the leaſt meaſure in any <hi>Member,</hi> tho for Conſcience ſake, they may be of a differing apprehenſion in ſome things; and therefore, the Apoſtle, <hi>He became all to all,</hi> weak, or ſtrong; and ſaid, <hi>bear one anothers Burdens,</hi> and <hi>bear one with another;</hi> and therefore he condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Baptiſe</hi> and <hi>Circumciſe,</hi> to win over, and endeavoured the encreaſe of their Faith and Underſtandings; not blind <hi>Conformity</hi> before Convincement, but ſaid, <hi>If any be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveal it,</hi> &amp;c. As their Faith encreaſed, ſo ſhould their Obedience. The Spirit, the Apoſtle was in, could receive thoſe that differed in Judgment and Practice in ſome things, and did not ſay they were erred from their meaſures; and if againſt Womens-Meetings, that the Univerſal Spirit could not receive them, but were careful not to offend the weak; would deny themſelves that which was lawful, for the benefit of the weak: therefore not of <hi>G. F</hi>'s, pretended Univerſal Spirit.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>G. F</hi>'s <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Letter is ſo jumbled together, ſeemingly diſowning, and yet owning the Paper too: but take them either ways; if they diſown, then that manifeſts a difference; if they own it, then they plainly manifeſt themſelves to be what the Diſſenting Party hath objected againſt them many Years (only <hi>G. F. &amp;c.</hi> have imperiouſly and wrongfully born them down) <hi>Viz.</hi> That they do in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62825:6"/>
their Actings contradict their Principles and Doctrine; that is, they (as the <hi>Phariſees</hi>) ſay, and do not: for it is evident by the ſcope of their Letter, that they are diſſatisfied with the wording of it, and that latter Clauſe which admits a particular meaſure, may differ from the general, alſo afraid of its Publication, knowing they cannot juſtifie it, and that it is that they have been charged for practiſing theſe many years, and for this cauſe many have and do diſſent from them, whom they term, — <hi>gone from the Power of God, and Oppoſers of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Goſpel: Setters up of Standards againſt Truth:</hi> and many other Names and marks of Sons of Perdition; when they have nothing elſe againſt them, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not ſubmitting to <hi>G. F</hi>'s Orders without Conviction: for <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. do not at all contradict the Principle, <hi>Of giving up all,</hi> only the ſubſcribing to it; nor deny but their <hi>Meetings</hi> have ſuch power, or ought to be given up to, only would inſinuate that it is done from the Univerſal Spirit of God; and all who do not ſo believe and act, <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spirit cannot receive,</hi> &amp;c. But all that fear God, beware of ſuch, who be thus given to change, and believe and act ſo contrary to what they ſay and pretend; and notwithſtanding the good words of the Apoſtle, in the latter end of <hi>G. F</hi>'s Letter, which be ſound; and had they kept themſelves to their primitive Teſtimony, and ſound Doctrine, as in <hi>Scripture,</hi> there had not been this Seperation: but having followed the Devices of their own Heads, with fair words and ſpeeches, they beguile many ſimple ones; but now their Folly is made manifeſt, and that they have only a Form of Godlineſs, but deny the Power thereof; therefore from ſuch turn away. And it's better to be by ſuch accounted <hi>Separates,</hi> than for their favour to deprive your ſelves of the benefit of your own meaſures of Light and Life, according to which all ſhall be at laſt Judged.</p>
               <p>As for the ſeeming diſlike (or blame) of the Judgment, from theſe following words in <hi>G. F</hi>'s Letter, <hi>Viz. This would make the Belief in the Light, and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Spirit in their own particulars, not one with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spirit in the ſaid Meetings.</hi> That this is a diſowning of, or a Reproof for the Judgment in general, or the <hi>giving up of all,</hi> &amp;c. is but a fallacious cover, as appears by his high commending and extolling them in the latter part of his Letter, in <hi>p.</hi> 5. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo his words to them he terms <hi>Stubborn</hi> and <hi>Wilful,</hi> that cannot <hi>give up all,</hi> &amp;c. of thoſe he ſaith, <hi>The Univerſal Spirit cannot receive that — thoſe that the Mens and Womens Meetings have not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spirit of God, they are erred from their own meaſures,</hi> &amp;c. What this <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spirit</hi> is that they ſo often mention, is ſhewed in the Introduction, and <hi>pag.</hi> 9. Alſo they ſay in <hi>W. F</hi>'s Book, <hi>Spiritual-Liberty,</hi> &amp;c. pag. 4. <hi>Thoſe that be left with the one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth, muſt be of one Mind, they cannot be otherwiſe.</hi> Theſe words, <hi>be of one Mind,</hi> and having <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> with <hi>G. F</hi>'s <hi>Womens-Meetings,</hi> is all to the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as the <hi>Barbadoes Judgment,</hi> only that is more naked, and plain, and not ſo ſubtilly worded, as ſome here could have done it, for we muſt believe and practice juſt as they do, or would have us, or elſe no Unity, which implyes as much <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving up</hi> as the <hi>Barbadoes Judgment</hi> doth, as is further manifeſted by their ſevere Judgments againſt thoſe that cannot ſo do, and by rendring them Apoſtates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62825:7"/>
And <hi>G. F's, &amp;c.</hi> diſlike or blameing them is not for their <hi>giving up all,</hi> &amp;c. but for the latter Clauſe of the <hi>Judgment,</hi> which admits that a particular meaſure may differ, or not agree with the generally in the <hi>Mens</hi> and <hi>Womens-Meetings,</hi> who be too much ſwayed and over-ruled by his Party, and termed the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spirit of God:</hi> but this Judgment proves that their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spirit,</hi> and Ruling Party have erred; therefore Particulars ought not to have Unity with them, but teſtifie againſt them. It's evident from the <hi>Aſian,</hi> and all others Churches ſince down to this very <hi>Barbadoes</hi> Church, that the Univerſal Ruling Part have erred, and been teſtified againſt and reproved by particulars, as <hi>G. F's</hi> Lording Spirit in himſelf and Party have been, altho they ſeem to be ſo reſolved, as that they will have the <hi>Power, Authority,</hi> and <hi>Judgment,</hi> &amp;c. and will Govern; and rather than they will want a Place where, and Subjects over whom to govern, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they will ſtretch their <hi>Power</hi> over the Conſciences of their Brethren, even in the <hi>Seat</hi> or <hi>Throne</hi> of Chriſt, as is further manifeſt from <hi>R. B</hi>'s <hi>Anarchy,</hi> &amp;c. vindicated by the <hi>Second-days Meeting</hi> in their (falſe) <hi>Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>page</hi> 57. Where they ask this Queſtion, <hi>If in no Caſe of Conſcience the Church of Chriſt hath Power to give ſuch poſitive Sentence as is juſt and righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When they mention the <hi>Church of Chriſt</hi> in reſpect to this preſent Age, that they mean only themſelves, ſeems evident from the ſaid <hi>R. B</hi>'s <hi>Anarchy,</hi> &amp;c. p. 43. Alſo <hi>Judas or the Jews,</hi> &amp;c. p. 28. Where they term themſelves the <hi>Body of Chriſt:</hi> And in other Writings, <hi>they the People of God, and none elſe.</hi> Alſo when they mention the <hi>Government and good Ordinances of Chriſt,</hi> or in his <hi>Church,</hi> it is evident, they mean ſome new invented Formalities, and Ceremonies of their own, and not fundamental Principles, according to the Precepts and Examples of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, mentioned in the holy Scripture. Therefore their terms of the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> and pretentions to <hi>Juſt and Righteous Sentences and Judgment,</hi> are but Covers, and ſuch Robes hath the Woman which ſitteth on the <hi>Scarlot coloured Beaſt,</hi> been arrayed with in all Ages ſince the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending themſelves the <hi>True Church,</hi> and their <hi>Sentences</hi> and <hi>Judgment, Juſt</hi> and <hi>Righteous,</hi> as you do; and you have provided Weapons for them, that may in time, prove to your own hurt, <hi>IF YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> BE NOT ALL OF ONE MIND AND J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DGMENT.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For if you gain but that Point, to have Power <hi>in any Caſe of Conſcience, to give poſitive Sentence, WHO but YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  </hi> (who ſay, <hi>you are the CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH</hi>) muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine in what Caſes, ſo that it is in what Caſes you pleaſe, which is as good as if you had ſaid, <hi>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> HAVE POWER (IF YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> PLEASE) IN ANY CASE OF CONSCIENCE, TO GIVE POSITIVE SENTENCE AND J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DGMENT.</hi> And I ſee not, but if that you have ſuch abſolute Power in <hi>Caſes of Conſcience,</hi> but that you may alſo claim it in <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> and have Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to determine, as <hi>R. B.</hi> ſaith, <hi>To remove ſuch Differences by your poſitive Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</hi> And let the wiſe in Heart Judge how little this is leſs than <hi>all Spirituals</hi> and <hi>Temporals,</hi> according to the <hi>Barbadoes Judgment,</hi> for if any difference be between the Lording, Ruling, Univerſal Party, and ſome other Particular, the Univerſal Party will not fail to ſay, <hi>They be the true Church, &amp; have Power, &amp; if we
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62825:7"/>
muſt be all of one Mind and Judgment.</hi> Whoſe Judgment ought we to be of, but the <hi>Church</hi>'s, (Viz. YOURS) being in the true Faith, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> BEHOLD WHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER THIS DRIVES: And according to <hi>C. Taylors</hi> Doctrine, it may be ſaid, as in his Book <hi>Something,</hi> &amp;c. p. 35. <hi>FOR O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHT I KNOW,</hi> you will centre in <hi>ROME,</hi> and ſay, <hi>It is the poſitive, juſt, and righteous Sentence of the Church.</hi> (It is truly ſaid in <hi>Addr. to Prot.</hi> p. 144. <hi>An Impoſing Church — will be both Judge and Party</hi>) So that according to this Doctrine, you have a Charter <hi>to give poſitive Sentence in any Caſes of Conſcience,</hi> &amp;c. TO HAVE AND TO HOLD, (if you can) until you pleaſe to give Setence againſt your ſelves. And when the <hi>Second-days Meeting</hi> have reſolved when that ſhall be, and in what Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and in what not, you have Power to give poſitive Sentence; then their need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Queſtion before mentioned gendring to Strife and Bondage, may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; but until then, them and their Queſtion to be avoided, according to the Advice of the Apoſtle, <hi>Beware of the Conciſion, beware of Evil Workers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pray conſider what ſentence had poor <hi>Micajah,</hi> among the 400 Prophets, the 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.24. <hi>When Zedekiah went near and ſmote him, and ſaid, Which way went the Spirit of the Lord from me to ſpeak unto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> &amp; other of the Prophets, from the Church in their days, who could ſpeak high words, ſaying, <hi>The Lord lived that brought them out of the Land of AEgypt, and out of the Houſe of Bondage.</hi> Alſo conſider what poſitive Sentences Chriſt and his Apoſtles had from the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and Ruling Party of the Church, who garniſhed the Sepulchres of the Prophets, ſaying, <hi>If they had lived in their days, they would not have killed them:</hi> And thought highly of themſelves, ſaying, <hi>They were Abrahams Seed, and never were in Bondage,</hi> and reputed themſelves <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Overſeers, and thoſe to whom God hath given Counſel, Authority, and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to, and as the true Church;</hi> gave <hi>poſitive Sentences, and as they thought, Juſt and Righteous, againſt the Servants of Chriſt:</hi> and demanded by whoſe Authority they did thoſe things, as ſome of you have done, when one Speak, or Pray in your Meeting; and becauſe not in exact Conformity to <hi>G.F</hi>'s Laws, therefore have asked, <hi>Doth, or did</hi> G. F. <hi>allow, or approve of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo conſider, when all <hi>Aſia</hi> was turned aſide, and all men forſook <hi>Paul,</hi> and none ſtood by him, only ſome few Particulars, What was their poſitive <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences?</hi> Doubtleſs they thought them juſt and righteous, and obligatory, as they were the Church, being the Univerſal and Ruling Party. Therefore without Evidence from Scripture, or by the Spirit in our own Hearts, of the Juſtice and Righteouſneſs of your poſitive Sentences and Orders, they are but the Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Men, altho taught for Doctrines.</p>
               <p>And the Light or Spirit of Chriſt within, is a ſurer Guide and Leader to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular, than the Unity, or being of one Mind and Judgment with any of <hi>G. F</hi>'s, &amp;c. Mens and Womens Meetings: For in the New <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> coming down from God out of Heaven, in which <hi>John</hi> ſaw no <hi>Temple,</hi> neither had it need of <hi>Sun</hi> or <hi>Moon,</hi> but the Glory of the LORD <hi>and the</hi> LAMB is the Light thereof.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62825:8"/>
               <p>WHat is here afore-wrote, is not as a full Anſwer or Detection of the depths of Satan, and Myſtery of Iniquity that is couched under, or lies hidden in this Judgment aſſerted in the Paper from <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and the ſeeming Anſwer of diſlike thereto, given by <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. but only as a Mite from one, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to preſent Ability, to manifeſt his deteſtation of all ſuch Principles and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But I doubt not but there will be ſome of greater Ability, who ſhall contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute much more to the uncovering <hi>Her</hi> who hath long ſat as a Queen, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived many, yet ſays, <hi>I ſhall not ſee Widdowhood nor Sorrow;</hi> becauſe her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are many and mighty, through the Power they have received from that Beaſt on which ſhe rides, and will ſuffer none to buy nor ſell in their <hi>Market,</hi> but who receive her Mark in their Forehead or Hand. For notwithſtanding their Judgment ſeems ſuch bare-fac'd <hi>Popery,</hi> and ſo contrary to their pretended Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, yet obſerve how <hi>G.F. &amp;c.</hi> treat the Authors, <hi>Viz. We know your Care and tenderneſs for Truth, and that you aim at the beſt Things, and are manifeſtly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Epiſtle of Chriſt, written with the Spirit of the Living God, which will bring you to the City of the Living God,</hi> &amp;c. And not one ſharp Reproof in all, only Caution for fear of its Publication, and diſlike that any particular meaſure ſhould not be one with their <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Womens-Meetings,</hi> &amp;c. But when we conſider the Names and Terms are given to others that profeſs the ſame Faith, and agree in all Things, except as aforeſaid, <hi>Viz.</hi> Something about <hi>Womens-Meetings,</hi> and ſome Forms of Marriages, &amp;c. they for this conſcientious forbearing to practice ſuch Things as they have no Faith in, are termed <hi>Apoſtates, departed from the Truth, ſuch as the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Spirit cannot receive,</hi> &amp;c. By all which we may ſee how they would hedge up the way to God, and leave no Door to come in by, but <hi>G. F</hi>'s Forms; nay, not only ſo, but tie up, or limit God, that if he reveals any thing to any particular, he muſt give up all to the general, and if they have not Unity with it, muſt cleave to the general againſt that particular Meaſure of Knowledge or Manifeſtation in himſelf; but I think hereby is plainly manifeſted that there be ſuch Innovators as <hi>W. Rogers</hi> hath mentioned in his Book, <hi>Viz. The Chrictian-Quaker diſtinguiſhed from the Apoſtate and Innovator.</hi> Which Title <hi>C. Taylor</hi> ſaith, is <hi>notorious Blaſphemy.</hi> But hereby it not only appears that the Title is proper, and no <hi>Blaſphemy:</hi> but alſo that there was juſt Cauſe for <hi>W. R</hi>'s writing that Book; for the Cauſe why thoſe, they call <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> ſeparate from them, is not out of any diſlike or denyal of the Principles of Truth (altho they ſay all that oppoſe them be gone from Truth) but in oppoſition to their Uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Authority over Peoples Conſciences in Religious Matters, and requiring Conformity to their Orders, before or without Conviction.</p>
               <p>This is the chief Cauſe of their hard Speeches, and falſe Accuſations againſt thoſe they term <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> and <hi>Seperates,</hi> and ſay, <hi>In the Name of the Lord they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to give Battle where-ever they meet that Spirit.</hi> But others are reſolved in the Spirit of the Lamb, not to bow to their <hi>Image,</hi> having ſeen that they ſhould, as they have done, manifeſt themſelves to be what they are, even empty <hi>Clouds.</hi> The Lord open the Underſtandings of all the ſimple-hearted among them (as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62825:8"/>
I believe there be many) and preſerve all blameleſs, and in Love, that they may have no juſt Cauſe to ſpeak evil of you: but ſeparate from ſuch who have a Form of Godlineſs, and high ſwelling words of <hi>Church-Power</hi> and <hi>Goſpel-Order</hi> (which they have made to themſelves, and are bowing to, even the Work of their own hands, as appears by the foregoing and following Lying Prophecy of <hi>S. Eccles.</hi>) and have your Minds girt up towards the Lord, and your Converſation as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Goſpel, in Meekneſs and Fear, not terrified by their high ſwelling Words; and ſeeing the evil Effects of forſaking the Teaching of the Lord by his Spirit, to give up to <hi>Mens</hi> and <hi>Womens-Meetings,</hi> and <hi>Orders,</hi> beware leſt you be carried away with the Errour of the wicked, and fall from your own Stedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but endeavour to grow in Grace, and of the Knowledge of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to whom alone be Obedience and Glory for ever: which is the deſire of my Heart, as for my ſelf, ſo for all that deſire to follow the Lord, and that we may be kept from Idols.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <head>Here follows the Falſe Propheſy of <hi>S. E.</hi> taken out of his Letter which he (accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with two eminent Friends, and Eſpouſers of <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Party) delivered to <hi>J. S.</hi> who lived ſome years after, notwithſtanding his predicting the contrary.</head>
                           <p>O <hi>JOHN STORY,</hi> What haſt thou done againſt the Lord and thy own Soul! Thou haſt divided the Heritage of God; and the good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances which Chriſt Jeſus hath ſet up in his Church haſt thou contemned, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Womens-Preachings,</hi> and <hi>Womens-Meetings;</hi> therefore will the Lord throw Contempt upon thee; and if thou doſt not repent ſpeedily, miſerable will be thy End— O how haſt thou loſt thy Place and Dignity which thou hadſt amongſt the Saints in Light! and now to be numbred amongſt the Rebellious. — If ever thou find Mercy with the Lord, go home to the <hi>North</hi> with ſpeed, and break up the Divided Meetings, which thou and <hi>John Wilkingſon</hi> have been Inſtrumental to divide from the Body of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt — The Anger of the Lord is chiefly againſt thee; and thou art bound with two Bonds: for the Church and Brethren have bound thee on Earth, and thou art ſurely bound in Heaven; and this is the Teſtimony of Jeſus to thee; neither ſhalt thou be able to get from under theſe Bonds, till thou art reconcil'd to the Brethren — [i.e. <hi>ſubmit to</hi> G. F. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] O haſt to the Work aboveſaid, leſt the Wrath of the Lord overtake thee before it be done, and be reconciled to <hi>G. F.</hi> who is God's Friend, and the Servant of the Living God, and <hi>Great Apoſtle</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, — Haſt away to the <hi>North,</hi> for thy time is ſhort, and go quickly thou and thy Brother, if poſſible you may bring again to the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, thoſe ye have ſcattered, leſt their Blood be required at your Hands; — Ariſe quickly, and be going, for this is the Word of the Lord to thee, <hi>Viz. <hi>That this Year ſhalt thou</hi> (John Story) <hi>die, becauſe thou haſt Taught Rebellion againſt the Living God.</hi>
                              </hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>SOLOMON ECCLES.</signed>
                              <dateline>
                                 <date>1st. <hi>day of the</hi> 1ct <hi>Month,</hi> 1677.</date>
                              </dateline>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62825:9"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>READER,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>OBſerve what this <hi>S. E.</hi> (one of <hi>G. F</hi>'s Preachers) delivers in the Name of the LORD, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That their <hi>Womens-Preachings</hi> and <hi>Womens-Meetings</hi> are the Good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances which Chriſt hath ſet up in his Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That being reconciled (<hi>i. e.</hi> ſubmitting) to <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Impoſing Party, is the only way to find Mercy with the Lord.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. (who call themſelves the Body of Friends) he terms the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That great Lye he delivered in the Name of the Lord, <hi>Viz. THIS YEAR SHALT THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  </hi> (JOHN STORY) <hi>DIE,</hi> &amp;c. Who was then Ill, and not like to live long, but yet lived about four years after.</p>
               <p>This is here inſerted, that all who read or hear it, may fear, and beware of taking the Name of the Lord in vain. Alſo of having <hi>G. F.</hi> or any Perſons, or their Orders in Admiration, as this <hi>S. E.</hi> and others his Brethren and Preachers of <hi>G. F</hi>'s Party have ſo frequently done, as appears by the Titles they have given <hi>G. F. Viz. One greater than</hi> Moſes, <hi>a Prophet indeed, — It was ſaid of Chriſt, he was in the World, the World was made by Him, and the World knew Him not; ſo it may be ſaid of this true Prophet, whom</hi> John <hi>ſaid he was not, but thou ſhalt feel this Prophet one day, as heavy as a Milſtone upon thee, and though the World knoweth him not, yet he is known.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>G. F.</hi> hath been ſtiled, <hi>The Father of many Nations, whoſe Life hath reached to us thy Children, even to the Iſles afar off, whoſe Being and Habitation is in the Power of the Higheſt, in which thou Rules and Governs in Righteouſneſs, and thy Kingdom is Eſtabliſhed in Peace, and the Encreaſe thereof is without End.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe and many more have been given him, which I do not underſtand that he diſowned or teſtified againſt, but rather owned and approved of them, as it ſeems to appear by his cauſing, or at leaſt ſuffering thoſe Expreſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be Communicated to others, See alſo a Blaſphemous and Idolatrous Letter in p. 7 of 5th. BABELS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now theſe have been covered, Juſtified, or excuſed, but others that conſcientiouſly diſſent from their Ceremonies, they are perſecuted with Rigour and falſe Accuſations. Oh Was ever greater Partiality and reſpect of Perſons from ſuch high Pretenders to Chriſtianity! And if Trees may be known by their Fruits, theſe are evil Ones. Therefore dear Friends, be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from theſe unclean things, for ſuch Principles and Practices, are <hi>Babylons Brats</hi> (who is to be made naked to the ſhame of her Lovers) and happy ſhall thoſe be who daſh them againſt the Stones, but wo to them that give ſuck to, and nouriſh them. Think me not your Enemy, becauſe I deal plainly with you, for it is in Love to Truth, and abhorrence of Impoſition, unlimited Power, Impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, blind, and unacceptable Obedience, I deſire the Lord to give you to know what is his good and acceptable Will. Recommending you to the Spirit of Grace in your own Hearts, whereby you may be preſerved blameleſs in this crooked Generation. To God only be Glory and Eternal Honour for ever.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
